Leo King collection of railroad photographs
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
Leo King collection of railroad photographs
1937-2001
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
King, Leo
2006.1
4 linear feet 10 archival binders, 1 slide case, 1 box Approximately 14,000 images including photographs, black-and-white film, slides, and digital images.
Photographs, negatives, slides, and digital images by Leo King, from his collection of approximately 14,000 images. The collection spans more than fifty years and thirty states, focusing on Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and Alaska. Major areas of focus include tourist and scenic railroads, structures including depots and engine terminals, and railroads in the landscape.
Selected Search Terms
Countries
United States; Canada
States/Provinces
Alaska; Alberta, CA; Arizona; California; Colorado; Connecticut; Florida; Georgia; Illinois; Louisiana; Kansas; Maine; Maryland; Massachusetts; Michigan; Minnesota; Missouri; Montana; New Hampshire; New Jersey; New York; North Carolina; Oregon; Pennsylvania; Rhode Island; South Carolina; Texas; Utah; Vermont; Washington; West Virginia
Railroads
American Locomotive Company; Alaska Railroad; Amtrak; Atchison, Topeka & Santa Fe Railway; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad; Baltimore & Ohio Railroad; Bangor & Aroostook Railroad; Bay Colony Railroad; Bessemer & Lake Erie Railroad; Boston & Maine Railroad; Brimstone & New River Railroad; Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad; Burlington Northern Railroad; Canadian Pacific; Central of Georgia Railway; Central Railroad of New Jersey; Central Vermont Railway; Chesapeake & Ohio Railway; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul & Pacific Railroad; Colorado & Wyoming Railway; Conrail; Delaware & Hudson Railway; Denver & Rio Grande Railway; Elgin, Joliet, & Eastern Railway; Erie Railroad; Great Northern Railway; Illinois Central Railroad; Kansas City Southern Railway; Lehigh & New England Railroad; Long Island Rail Road; Maine Central Railroad; Minneapolis & St. Louis Railway; Missouri Pacific Railroad; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; New York, Ontario & Western Railway; New York, Susquehanna & Western Railway; Nickel Plate Railroad; Railway Norfolk Southern Railway; Penn Central Railroad; Pere Marquette Railway; Philadelphia & Reading Railroad; Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad; Providence & Worcester Railroad; Savannah & Atlanta Railroad; Seaview Railroad; Southern Pacific Railroad; St. Louis-San Francisco Railroad; Union Pacific Railroad; Valley Railroad; Wabash Railroad
Subjects
Photography of railroads; Railroads--Pictorial works
Biographical Note
Leo King (1938-2011) grew up in Providence, Rhode Island, and developed an avid interest in trains while in grammar school. Leo had several careers, including serving in the Air Force and a career as a bridge operator over the Connecticut River. Beginning in 1988, he worked for Amtrak between Boston and New Haven as a train director and block operator. For thirty years he was an editor and writer and contributed articles to Railfan & Railroad, RailNews, and Passenger Train Journal. Leo also worked as a radio broadcast anchor and reporter for various Rhode Island radio stations.
He photographed avidly wherever he lived and worked, even in Alaska with the Air Force. He retired to Middleburg, Florida, near Jacksonville, in 2002, maintaining his interest in writing about railroads and in railroad photography, as long as he was physically able.
Scope and Content Note
The Leo King collection includes approximately 14,000 images of various formats including about 550 photographs, 750 35mm and glass slides, 2,100 negatives, and 10,000 documents and digital files. The photographs range from 1937 to 2001, covering more than thirty states in the USA and over fifty different railroads. The collection includes approximately 200 photographs by other photographers and railroad memorabilia that was collected by Leo King throuhout his life.
The collection has a strong focus domestically in Rhode Island, Massachusetts, Alaska, and New England with the Alaska Railroad; Union Pacific; New York, New Haven and Hartford; and Amtrak, among others. Much of the collection focuses on the Alaska Railroad through Seward, Whittier, and Anchorage. The images emphasize locomotives, scenic railroad companies, railroad landscapes, and railroad-related buildings such as stations, depots, engine houses, and museums.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged by type of material following Leo King's original order. It is organized by prints, slides, negatives, and miscellaneous materials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Leo King donated his photograph collection to the Center to catalog and preserve on May 12, 2006.
© 2015, Center for Railroad Photograph & Art
Digitized Versions Available
Images from this collection have been digitized and are available through CRP&A's online collections portal. Selected photographs are also publicly available on Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn and Flickr.
Related CRP&A Publications
Lothes, Scott, ed. Significant Images of Railroading. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2016.
"Leo King Views Work." Railroad Heritage No. 10 (2004).
- New York, New Haven and Hartford, 1950-1955; Series 1.1; Providence, Rhode Island and Boston, Massachusetts; 353 negatives (Binder King-NewHaven-01)
  States/Provinces
  Massachusetts; Rhode Island
  Railroads
  New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad
- Anchorage, 1968, July 4; Series 2.1; Anchorage, Alaska; 454 35mm slides (Binder King-Anchorage-2)
  Alaska
  Alaska Railroad
- Anchorage, 1970; Series 3.1; Anchorage, Alaska; 21 negatives (Binder King-Alaska-3)
- Golden Spike Ceremony, 1973, July 15; Series 3.2; Anchorage, Alaska; 115 negatives (Binder King-Alaska-3)
- Whittier Shuttle, 1973, July 15; Series 3.3; Anchorage, Alaska and Neanna, Alaska; 308 negatives (Binder King-Alaska-3)
- Alaska, 1964-1973; Series 3.4; Anchorage, Alaska; 588 negatives (Binder King-Alaska-3)
- Press, 1954-1955; 4.1; 142 press photos and builder's cards (Binder King-Press-4)
  Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway; Missouri Pacific Railroad
- Press Photos, 1955; Series 5.1; New York, New York; 103 press photos and postcards (Binder King-Press-5)
  New York
- East Side Tunnel, 1950-1952; 1969-2000; Series 6.1; Providence, Rhode Island; 702 photographs and negatives (Binder King-EastSide-6)
  Rhode Island
  New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; Conrail; Canadian Pacific Railway; CSRX; Providence & Worcester Railroad
- Northeast Construction, 1954; 1993, July 1; Series 7.1; Providence, Rhode Island; Boston, Massachusetts; West Palm Beach, Florida; Connecticut; 213 photographs (Binder King-Construction-7)
  Connecticut; Florida; Massachusetts; Rhode Island
- Providence Photos, 1940; 1954; 1997; Series 8.1; Providence, Rhode Island; 212 photographs (Binder King-Photos-8)
  Alaska; Rhode Island
  Amtrak
- Alaska Railroad Slides, 1995; Series 9.1; 386 slides, glass plate negatives, and negatives (Binder King-Slides-9)
  Arizona; Alaska; Connecticut
  Alaska Railroad; Amtrak; Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railway; Providence & Worcester Railroad; Union Pacific Railroad
- Southwest Glass Slides, 1937-1947; Series 10.l; 51 glass plate negatives (Binder King-Slides-10)
  Arizona; Minnesota
- Model Railroad Clippings, 1971-1973; 2001; Series 11.1; Amtrak Operating Rules; Dixie Line pamphlet.; Newspaper and magazine clippings (Binder King-News-11)
- Digital files and images, circa 2000; Series 12.1; 10,303 images 48 CDs (Binder King-CDs-12)
  Digital images and files from the CDs were copied to an external hard drive.